hey guys professor brett contreras here
uh
i realize i never really discussed an
article i got published in uh the scj
the straight strength and conditioning
journal this year the title was are all
hip extension exercises created equal
and so
uh this was a very cool paper that got
published and i wanted to take the the
time to explain the article for those of
you who aren't able to download it if
you are an nsca member then you'll have
access to the journal you should pull it
up i'll provide a link in my blog post
about this where i embed this video but
uh
anyway the whole
question of the article is are all hip
extension exercises created equal
so
what i did was i picked three different
hip extension exercises that most
strength coaches would feel
are kind of the same because they're the
same movement pattern
the horizontal back extension the 45
degree back extension and then the good
morning exercise every one of those
involves bending at the hips and
straightening out so they're all three
different hip extensions and the legs
remain relatively straight
uh so they're straight leg hip extension
exercise sure in the good morning
they'll bend a little more uh the knees
will bend a little more but the whole
point is these are different exercises
but they're from different vectors
um
and so
uh i kind of illustrated here the
different
uh positions so this would be a the
bottom of a good morning and then the
top of the good morning you know
would be like that so this is the bottom
where you're bent in half and then you
stand up the 45 degree hyper this is the
bottom
and then you would raise the torso up
and end up like that and then the
horizontal back extension you start out
like this
and then you end up
out here so if you think about doing
these exercises just use common sense
from what you know about doing them the
good morning you're standing here with a
bar like this this is easy okay you can
hang out here all day
then you bend over it becomes harder and
harder and harder the hardest point is
at the very bottom then you stand back
up
so the hardest part is at the bottom
think about the horizontal back
extension
if you're in a horizontal back extension
you go to the bottom you can just hang
out there all day sure it might be
stretching your hamstrings but it's not
that hard but then you come up to the
top especially if you're holding load it
becomes very difficult so the hardest
point is at the top of a horizontal back
extension so
those are flip flops of each other so
basically what i did was i took a
a six foot tall guy i just made a
hypothetical reference
athletic individual he's six foot tall
okay
weighs 200 pounds
and uh uses a hundred pounds external
resistance so picture a guy who's six
feet tall
weighs 200 pounds
uh athletic looking dude
and he's using a hundred extra pounds
resistance for these exercises
and he's gonna do a good morning a back
extension and a 45 degree hyper
well if you can calculate the hip the
hip extension torque it's pretty easy to
do so
all you're doing is um you have to
create the calculate the hip extension
torque uh the instantaneous hip
extension torque of the torso itself and
then of the the weight
and basically
you've got like a you know a
lever arm the distance from like the
load
to the hip joint and then you've got a
load and you just multiply the load
times that lever arm
and to get the torque and then you add
up the torque imposed by the torso
itself or actually the head arms and
trunk and then you add up add that to
the
torque imposed by the load you've got
your hip excitatory so here's what
happened
here um here's a graph
on the y-axis i have hip extension
torque which is measured in newton
meters
and on the x-axis i have the hip joint
angle which is in degrees
here i have 90 degrees
135 degrees at 180 degrees so the 90
degree position is this bent over
position
135 degrees so 90 degrees is bent over
completely 135 is right here 180 right
here
so uh
basically what we talked about earlier
the hardest part of the good morning so
let's plot the good morning first the
hardest part of the good morning was at
90 degrees at the very bottom at a hip
joint angle of 90 degrees
that actually imposed
newton meters of torque out at the hips
okay when you got to 135 degrees now
it's at 338 meters of torque
and then when you get to 180 degrees
which you're standing straight up
there's no torque at the hips the bar is
centered right over the hips so when
you're standing like this there's no
torque output
so it's like this
okay
so you
connect these
and you get something that looks like
this okay
now i'm going to do the horizontal back
extension well we talked about when
you're at the bottom of a back extension
that's the easiest position there's no
torque you're just hanging out
there's no load on the hips okay
when you
get halfway up you're at 338 and when
you reach full extension you're now at
the hardest part which is
so
you plot these and it looks like that
notice that these are complete inverses
of one another
they kind of form an x
so the the torque
angle curves this is a torque angle
curve that i'm
creating the torque angle curves of the
good morning and the back extension are
inverses of one another and here's
what's interesting the 45 degree hyper
if you notice
the hardest position for the 45 degree
hyper is actually going to be
right here because this is where the
load is furthest out from the hip joint
from here to here and from here to here
is not as much distance if that makes
sense so the hardest part of the 45
degree hyper is actually
right here in the 135 degree angle
position
but at the bottom at the top
you're getting
so this curve looks like this
okay so what in the world does this mean
well
my very good friend brad schoenfeld he
wrote an article uh three years ago that
was published in the journal of strength
and conditioning research
called
mechanisms of muscle hypertrophy and
their application to resistance training
a very good article
what he proposed was hypertrophy has
three aspects to it
um
kind of the mechanisms three primary
mechanisms that create hypertrophy
one of them
is
mechanical tension
and this is probably the most important
the second one is
metabolic stress
and the third one is
muscle damage
okay
so these are the three primary
mechanisms of muscle hypertrophy
well what exercises creates the most
mechanical tension here all three of
them have the same peak tensions just in
different ranges of motion
well if you know anything about gluteus
maximus emg you will know that you
actually get higher glute maximus
gluteus maximus activation at n range
hip extension compared to when you're
bent over
so the back extension will give you
higher glute activation just because
when you're standing up if you squeeze
the glutes as hard as possible you will
actually get higher glute activation
than when you're bent over and you flex
like if you did squat all the way down
squeeze your glutes your glutes won't
activate as high as when you're standing
up squeezing your glutes the glutes
are um you know neurologically more
efficient standing up or full hip
extension
so for the glutes what gives you the
most peak tension for the glutes it's
going to be the back extension exercise
right here so this is going to be the
best
exercise repeat tension on the glutes
all right if we uh
look at the hamstrings though the
biggest load on the hamstrings is going
to be when you're bent over stretched
and that's going to be the good morning
right here and if you think about it the
good morning when you bend over and
you're at the bottom that's going to
create the most muscle damage because
you're stretching the muscle under heavy
eccentric load
and so
if you want to create muscle damage to
the hamstrings you're going to do the
good morning
if you want to
create mechanical tension
for the glutes you're going to do the
back extension but think about this
which exercise here has the most mean
torah the most mean torque the most
average torque if you look at these
curves
the 45 degree hyper here
it never drops to zero there's always a
load and if you've ever done the 45
degree hyper you know that you have
constant tension on those hamstrings you
get a big burn and glutes and hamstrings
when you do these
so the 45 degree hyper is going to be
the best for the most
constant tension because
you know the you're always under load
the hips are always under load and so
blood never has a chance to escape if
blood can't escape because the muscles
keep contracting
the blood builds up and you get uh
you get metabolic stress so what's the
best exercise for metabolic stress
probably a 45 degree hyper so the 45
degree hyper best for
metabolic stress
the good morning is the best for
uh muscle damage
and the back extension is probably the
best for mechanical tension
so
what does this mean are all hip
extensions exercise created equal
no they're not they're very different
depending on their torque angle curves
these are the same movement pattern it's
straight leg
hip extension
but they have very unique torque angle
curves and they have different potential
applications now this is just
hypothetical at this point but i suspect
that if you uh the the exercise that
would give you the most glute
hypertrophy would probably be the back
extension of the 45 degree back
extension the exercise that would
probably give you the most
hamstring hypertrophy i'm not sure it
might be the good morning but what's
interesting about
exorcisms that create muscle damage such
as the good morning when you bend over
and kind of stretch the muscle under
heavy load and it has a big eccentric
load because it's stretched
you actually uh create that muscle
damage you create actually induces
sarcomere genesis sarcomeres in series
and it can increase fascicle weight then
when you increase fascicle length you
have more rapid muscle contractions
and so when you think about an exercise
like sprinting
right before the foot touches the ground
the hamstrings are at a long muscle
length
the glutes are a short muscle length at
ground contact so you want the
hamstrings strong at long muscle lengths
you want the glutes strong at short
muscle lengths for sprinting so
the good morning would be a great
exercise for
you know the hammies
the back extension a great exercise for
the glutes and the 45 degree hyper is
kind of in between the 45 so the good
morning strength and strengthens the
bottom portion the best
the 45 degree hyper the middle portion
the best and the back extension the end
portion the best so
again
i thought this was a very important
article it's the first article of its
kind it's the only article
that i've seen that addresses this stuff
it is cutting edge biomechanics
married to
you know hypertrophy research and that's
why brad and i get along so well because
my research and his research go hand in
hand
so anyway i hope you enjoyed the article
i hope you are the
video i hope you learned something
please remember to go to the blog
and check it out because i will uh
jot down i'll include the link and jot
down some info about it thank you very
much for watching